<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nauroz Ahmad</title>
    <description>Articles about marketing trends, case studies and tutorials.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 04:43:22 +0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 04:43:22 +0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Go beyond first names. Personalization is about a lot more.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Personalization in email marketing can be a great tool to grab your audience’s attention, but just adding someone’s name in the subject line or body of the email doesn’t always cut it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email marketing is still going strong. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/812060/email-marketing-revenue-worldwide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Statista&lt;/a&gt;, email marketing will be a $17.9 billion market by 2027. With an ROI of $36 for every $1 spent (source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.litmus.com/resources/email-marketing-roi/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Litmus&lt;/a&gt;), email marketing should be in the top 3 priorities for every business. But because everyone’s getting so many emails in their inbox every day, as marketers, we need to make sure our emails stand out, give value to readers, and make them look forward to more emails from you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Personalization” is a critical component of effective email marketing. It involves tailoring the content, tone, and delivery of your emails to match your subscribers’ specific interests and needs. Personalized emails are more likely to be opened, read, and acted upon than generic, one-size-fits-all emails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To personalize your emails, you need to know where your subscribers are coming from. And so, you need to track where your new leads come from, what information they consume, and how they interact with your site or app. Using this data, you can optimize your communication with them in not just email marketing but in other touchpoints as well. So make sure to invest your time and effort into integrating analytics tools into your site or app and making your communication relevant to your audience’s interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can personalize your emails in various ways, and different kinds of personalization can have different impacts on the effectiveness of your emails. See below a few essential types of personalization that you should consider incorporating into your email marketing strategy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;subject-lines&quot;&gt;Subject lines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the subscriber’s name in the subject line is a great idea. But you can have a more significant impact by referencing their past behavior or interest. Here are a few examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sign-up-from-a-blog-post&quot;&gt;Sign-up from a blog post&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone subscribed to your email list after reading an article about the latest trends in Google Ads. Since you know where they signed up, you can give them more value by writing your email according to their interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the subject line, you can say something like, “Hi Jim, Google just launched a new update.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the sub-text could be “This new update makes managing Performance Max campaigns easier.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;customer-of-a-local-business&quot;&gt;Customer of a local business&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example of a restaurant running an email blast about a new addition to its menu. It would be great to mention the location closest to your customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subject line: “Hey, Amy. We just launched our new habanero cheeseburger.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sub-text: “Visit the Park Ave branch and try it out!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See below a few more examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“John, we have new arrivals in the running shoes category.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Just for you, Tiffany: Our new collection of scrunchies.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Thanks for subscribing. Here’s your first exclusive offer.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These subject lines reference the subscriber’s specific interests or past behavior, increasing the chances that they will open the email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;segmentation&quot;&gt;Segmentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all get tons of emails these days, and it takes effort to cut through the noise and stand out. You need to send people emails that will be interesting and helpful to them. When you have user analytics data, you can segment your email list into groups based on their location, age group, interests, or behavior on your website or app. This allows you to create targeted, relevant content for different groups of subscribers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you run an online store selling clothing and home goods. You could segment your email list into “Clothing Interests” and “Home Goods Interests”. You can then create targeted, relevant content for each group. Send an email to the “Clothing Interests” group that features a new clothing collection and provides a special discount code for the clothing items. And for the “Home Goods Interests” group, you could send an email that features a new home goods collection and provides a special discount code for the home goods items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other ways to segment email lists are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Purchase history&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Website or app usage, pages visited&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engagement with previous emails&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Age, location, or gender&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a few examples, but there are many ways you can segment your email list to create targeted, relevant content for your subscribers. The key is to use data and analytics to identify meaningful segments and test different segmentation strategies to see what works best for your audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dynamic-content&quot;&gt;Dynamic content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Segmentation and dynamic content are related, but they are two different strategies used in email marketing. In segmentation, you divide your email list based on behavior, demographics, or interests. With Dynamic content, you can show different images, text, calls to action, and other elements to subscribers based on their behavior, demographics, interests, or other criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tools like MailChimp, SendGrid, and HubSpot have built-in features that help you make dynamic templates by loading different content if conditions match certain user types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you’re sending an email for a new product line. You know that one customer has been interested in shoes and another bought a dress just a week ago. You can design your email template so that the main image and title for the first customer are about shoes, and for the second customer, they’re about dresses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few other examples of dynamic content:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Location-based content: Show different content or offers to subscribers based on location. For example, you could show different store locations or events in a subscriber’s area.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Personalized calls to action: Show different calls to action to different subscribers based on their past behavior or interests. For example, if a subscriber has already made a purchase, you could show them a CTA to leave a review or refer a friend, while if they haven’t made a purchase yet, you could show them a CTA to make a purchase.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Customized email design: Show different email designs to subscribers based on their interests or past behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Language preference: Show different languages to subscribers based on their language preferences. This is especially useful for companies with a global reach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advantage of using dynamic content over segmentation is that it allows for an even more granular personalization. Showing different information within the same email can be used to address the specific needs or interests of the subscriber without sending multiple emails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practice, segmentation and dynamic content are often used together to create highly targeted, personalized email campaigns. For example, you could use segmentation to divide your email list into different groups and then use dynamic content to show different images or CTAs to each group based on their behavior or interests. By utilizing both segmentation and dynamic content, you can create a more comprehensive and effective email marketing strategy that addresses each subscriber’s specific needs and interests. This will help you to increase engagement, conversion rates, and overall ROI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;triggered-emails&quot;&gt;Triggered emails&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Triggered emails are automated emails based on a specific action or event, such as a subscriber’s behavior, a purchase, an abandoned cart, or a date. See below a few examples of triggered emails that you can use in your email marketing campaigns:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Welcome email:&lt;/strong&gt; Send a welcome email to new subscribers that confirm their subscription and provide them with information about your company or products.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abandoned cart email:&lt;/strong&gt; Send an email to customers who have added items to their cart but still need to complete their purchase, reminding them of the items in their cart and providing an incentive to complete the purchase.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purchase confirmation email:&lt;/strong&gt; Send a confirmation email to customers after they make a purchase, providing them with a receipt and other information about the purchase.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Post-purchase follow-up email:&lt;/strong&gt; Send an email a few days after purchase to ask for feedback or reviews about the products or services purchased.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anniversary email:&lt;/strong&gt; Send an email to customers on the anniversary of their first purchase or subscription, thanking them for their loyalty and offering them a special offer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Birthday email:&lt;/strong&gt; Send an email to the subscribers on their birthday with a special offer or discount.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Booking confirmation email:&lt;/strong&gt; Send a confirmation email to customers after booking, providing them with a confirmation number, booking details, and any additional information such as check-in/check-out times or cancellation policies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Booking reminder email:&lt;/strong&gt; Send an email to customers a few days before their booking, reminding them of their upcoming booking, providing them with any additional information such as directions or parking information, and asking if they need further assistance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Triggered emails are automated emails that are sent based on specific actions or events and are highly personalized and relevant. These emails have higher open and click-through rates than regular marketing emails.
Keep in mind that triggered emails should be added with a clear opt-in and opt-out option and should be compliant with the email regulations of your country/region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Triggered emails are an effective and easy way to give a personal touch to your relationship with your customer. Following up with your customers helps them understand that you care about your relationship. Use this opportunity to let them know how to reach out to you if they need help, follow you on social media, subscribe to your blog or video channel, or refer you to a friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;always-keep-testing&quot;&gt;Always keep testing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, you won’t nail your email marketing on your first try. And even if you do, you’ll always find room for improvement if you have data from your past email campaigns. Keep testing versions of copy, content, CTAs, and template design. Also, try different times, days of the week, and frequencies to determine which combination works best for your audience. Marketing is all about continuous improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, personalization is a crucial element of effective email marketing. By incorporating different types of personalization into your email marketing strategy, such as personalized subject lines, segmentation, dynamic content, triggered emails, and A/B testing, you can create highly targeted, relevant content that resonates with your subscribers and drives better results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that personalization is not only about putting a subscriber’s name into the email but also about providing the correct information and offers at the right time. It is vital to use data and analytics to track the performance of your personalized emails and continue to make improvements over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, collecting first-party data is a lot more critical these days after all the new privacy laws coming into effect in the last few years. &lt;a href=&quot;https://mixpanel.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mixpanel&lt;/a&gt; is an excellent tool for setting up detailed tracking on your website and app.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0500</pubDate>
        <link>/go-beyond-first-names-personalization-is-about-a-lot-more/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/go-beyond-first-names-personalization-is-about-a-lot-more/</guid>
        
        
        <category>email marketing</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
